Edward Goodrich Acheson Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edward Goodrich Acheson Papers 1872-1968 (bulk 1899-1930)
MSS49684
Acheson, Edward Goodrich, 1856-1931
13,000 items 48 containers plus 2 oversize 20.5 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Electrochemist, engineer, and inventor. Correspondence, diaries, biographical material, financial papers, laboratory notebooks relating to experiments and inventions, newspaper clippings, and other materials pertaining to Acheson's scientific work.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Acheson, Edward Goodrich, 1856-1931.; Acheson, Edward Goodrich, 1856-1931. A pathfinder: discovery, invention and industry; how the world came to have aquadag and oildag; also carborundum, artificial graphite and other valuable products of the electric furnace. The first of a series of educational biographical sketches of eminent inventors. 1910; Acheson, Edward Goodrich, 1887-1962--Correspondence.; Acheson, George Wilson, b. 1892--Correspondence.; Acheson, John Huyler, 1893-1938--Correspondence.; Acheson, Raymond Mahler, b. 1888--Correspondence.; Deringer, John P.--Correspondence.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931--Correspondence.; Hunt, Alfred E. (Alfred Ephraim), 1855-1899--Correspondence.; Huyler, John Seys, 1846-1910--Correspondence.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1937--Correspondence.; Nichols, E. L. (Edward Leamington), 1854-1937--Correspondence.; Rathenau, Walther, 1867-1922--Correspondence.; Smith, William Acheson--Correspondence.; Sprague, Edmund C.--Correspondence.; Szymanowitz, Raymond, b. 1898.
Organizations
Bakewell & Bakewell--Correspondence.; Carborundum Company (Niagara Falls, N.Y.); Cowles Electric Smelting and Aluminum Company--Correspondence.; Electrochemical Society--Correspondence.
Subjects
Chemistry.; Electrochemistry.; Inventions.
Occupations
Electrochemists.; Engineers.; Inventors.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Edward Goodrich Acheson, electrochemist, engineer, and inventor, were given to the Library of Congress by his children, Howard A. Acheson and Margaret A. Stuart, and by Raymond Szymanowitz in 1972.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the appropriate custodial division of the Library where they are identified as a part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edward Goodrich Acheson are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1856, Mar. 9 Born, Washington, Pa.
1872 Left school to make livelihood
1873 Invented and secured patent for rock-boring machine to be used in coal mines
1880 Moved to New York to find work in electrical industry
1880-1881 Assistant to Thomas A. Edison, Menlo Park, N.J.
1884 Married Margaret Maher
1885 Conducted unsatisfactory experiments on reduction of iron ore by natural gas
1894-1895 Invented carborundum Established Carborundum Co., and moved it to Niagara Falls, N.Y.
1894 Awarded the John Scott Medal by the Franklin Institute, for discovery of carborundum
1899 Incorporated Acheson Graphite Co.
1901 Awarded John Scott Medal for production of artificial graphite
1908 Invented and secured patent for siloxicon Awarded Rumford Medal of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences
1910 Published A Pathfinder: Discovery, Invention and Industry. New York: The Press Scrap Book
1928 Established Edward G. Acheson fund at Electrochemical Society
1929 Awarded Acheson Medal by Electrochemical Society
1931, July 6 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edward Goodrich Acheson (1856-1931) cover the period 1872-1968 with the bulk of the material falling between 1899 and 1930. They consist of diaries, letterbooks, laboratory notebooks, business and general correspondence, and miscellaneous material relating to Acheson's scientific career and his companies. The collection is arranged in Diaries, Letterbooks, Business Correspondence, General Correspondence, Miscellany, and Oversize series.
The diaries date from 1884 to 1931 and record Acheson's everyday activities and appointments. A typescript of his diaries, 1906-1926, is also included. Letterbooks date from 1889 to 1915 and relate primarily to his businesses.
The majority of the collection is included in the two correspondence series that reflect the organization of the files when they arrived at the Library. Business Correspondence consists of Acheson's communications with a relatively few people including his sons, Edward Goodrich Acheson (1887-1962), George Wilson Acheson, John Huyler Acheson, and Raymond Mahler Acheson; John P. Deringer; Thomas A. Edison; William Acheson Smith; and Edmund C. Sprague. Material in the General Correspondence series generally reflects Acheson's work and connections with firms that were founded by him and carry his name, including those established in Europe to commercialize the products and processes he had originated. Correspondents include Alfred E. Hunt, John Seys Huyler, Andrew W. Mellon, E. L. Nichols, and Walther Rathenau, and organizations such as Bakewell & Bakewell (patent attorneys), the Cowles Electric Smelting and Aluminum Company, and the Electrochemical Society. Included at the end of the General Correspondence are papers generated by Acheson's biographer, Raymond Szymanowitz, in collecting data relating to his study.
The Miscellany series includes financial notebooks, newspaper clippings, biographical sketches, a typescript of Acheson's autobiography, A Pathfinder, printed matter, scrapbooks, and scientific notebooks of his experiments and inventions. Oversize consists of two volumes of court proceedings relating to a case in which the Carborundum Company was involved in 1894.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in six series:
Diaries, 1884-1931
Letterbooks, 1889-1915
Business Correspondence, 1910-1934
General Correspondence, 1873-1968
Miscellany, 1872-1956
Oversize
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm74049684
Container List
- Diaries, 1884-1931 (Box 1)
  Diaries, address books, and appointment books.
  Arranged chronologically. Includes a transcript of the diaries, 1906-1926.
  - Diaries, 1884-1931, (32 vols.) (Box 1)
  - Address book, undated
  - Transcript of diaries, 1906-1926
- Letterbooks, 1889-1915 (Box 2-4)
  Bound volumes of copies of letters sent.
  Arranged chronologically. Volumes for 1894-1915 have indexes.
  - 1889-1890 (Box 2)
  - 1894-1895
  - 1895, Sept.-1896, June (Box 3)
  - 1896, June-1897, Nov.
  - 1897-1899
  - 1911-1912 (Box 4)
  - 1912-1915
- Business Correspondence, 1910-1934 (Box 5-15)
  Letters received, copies of letters sent, memoranda, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and therein chronologically.
  - Acheson, Edward G., Jr, Feb. 1910-Sept. 1926, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Acheson, George W., Apr. 1913-Dec. 1922, (2 folders)
  - Acheson, John Huyler, June 1910-Sept. 1926, (2 folders)
  - Acheson, Raymond M., 1915
  - Coe, Frank N., Nov. 1912-Feb. 1930, (11 folders) (Box 6)
  - Deringer, John P. (Box 7)
    - Mar. 1910-Dec. 1917, (7 folders)
    - 1918-1921, (8 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1922-1925, (8 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1926-1930, (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - Edison, Thomas A., 1881-1920
  - Edison Pioneers, 1918-1931
  - Scott, L. G., 1916-17, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Smith, William Acheson
    - 1905; Oct. 1912-May 1916, (6 folders)
    - June 1916-Dec. 1922, (8 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1923-29, 1933-1934, (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - Sprague, Edmund C.
    - Sept. 1915-Dec. 1917
    - 1918-1924, (5 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1925-1929, (4 folders) (Box 15)
- General Correspondence, 1873-1968 (Box 16-34)
  Correspondence, speeches, addresses, legal documents, agreements, and photostats.
  Arranged chronologically by year and thereunder alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - 1873 (Box 16)
  - 1876
  - 1878
  - 1879
  - 1880
  - 1881
    - General
    - Nichols, Edward L.
  - 1882
  - 1883
  - 1884
    - General
    - Adams, Milton F.
  - 1885
    - General
    - Cowles Electric Smelting and Aluminum Co.
    - Huyler
  - 1886
  - 1887
    - General
    - Nichols, Edward L.
  - 1888
    - General
    - Nichols, Edward L.
  - 1889
  - 1890
    - General
    - Marks, Louis B.
  - 1891
    - General
    - Nichols, Edward L.
  - 1892
    - General
    - Hunt, Alfred E.
    - Tesla, Nikola
  - 1893
    - General
    - Osterreichische Länderbank
  - 1894 (Box 17)
    - General
    - Holloway, James
    - Österreichische Länderbank
  - 1895
    - General
    - Bölling, F.
    - Fitzgerald, Francis A. J.
    - Kunz, George F.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Mott, Samuel D.
    - Tone, Frank J.
  - 1896
    - General
    - Huyler, John S.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Nichols, Edward L.
    - Rathenau, Walther
  - 1897
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Arison, William H.
    - Bakewell & Bakewell
    - Bölling, F. (Box 18)
    - Brydges & Co.
    - Chandler, C. F.
    - Foster & Freeman
    - Hipple, James
    - Holloway, James
    - Lüders, Richard
    - Lürmann, F.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Österreichische Länderbank
    - Rathenau, Walther
    - Ursell, B.
  - 1898
    - General
    - Bakewell & Bakewell
    - Brydges & Co.
    - Castner-Kellner Alkali Co., Ltd.
    - Diechmann (Gustav) & Sohn
    - Foster & Freeman
    - Graphitization of carbons
    - Hipple, James
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Talbot, Benjamin
    - Voss, Georeg and Co.
  - 1899 (Box 19)
    - General
    - Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Diechmann (Gustav) & Sohn
    - Lüders, Richard
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - National Carbon Co., (2 folders)
    - New York Central & Hudson River Railroad Co.
    - Obermayer (S.) Co.
  - 1900
    - General
    - Bakewell & Bakewell
    - Cowles Electric Smelting and Aluminum Co.
    - Foster & Freeman
    - Hipple, James
    - Kunz, George F.
    - Laureau, L. G.
    - Lundy's Lane house
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - National Graphite Co., (2 folders)
    - New York Central & Hudson River Railroad Co.
  - 1901 (Box 20)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Adams, Edward D.
    - Arison, William H.
    - Bakewell & Bakewell
    - Bellefonte Academy, Bellefonte, Pa.
    - Chandler, C. F.
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Foster & Freeman
    - International Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Kunz, George F.
    - Laureau, L. G.
    - Lundy's Lane house
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Pan American Exposition, Buffalo, N.Y.
    - Siloxicon; Egyptianized clay
  - 1902 (Box 21)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Adams, Edward D.
    - Bakewell & Bakewell
    - Bellefonte Academy, Bellefonte, Pa.
    - Day, David T.
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Fitzgerald, Francis A. J.
    - Foster & Freeman
    - Hunt, Alfred E.
    - Huyler, John S.
    - International Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Lundy's Lane house
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Rathenau, Walther
    - Siloxicon; Egyptianized clay
    - Thomson, Elihu
    - Ward (Fred) & Son
  - 1903 (Box 22)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Adams, Edward D.
    - Bellefonte Academy, Bellefonte, Pa.
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Foster & Freeman
    - International Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Kunz, George F.
    - Oatka Gypsum Co.
    - Packard Motor Car Co.
    - St. Louis Exposition, St. Louis, Mo.
    - Silixocon; Egyptianized clay, (2 folders)
    - Ward (Fred) & Son
  - 1904 (Box 23)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Acheson Co.
    - Adams, Edward D.
    - American Ceramic Society
    - Bellefonte Academy, Bellefonte, Pa.
    - Foster & Freeman
    - Holloway, James
    - Hunt, Alfred E.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Packard Motor Car Co.
    - Ries, Heinrich
    - St. Louis Exposition, St. Louis, Mo.
    - Siloxicon; Egyptianized clay
  - 1905
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Acheson Co.
    - Adams, Edward D.
    - Arison, William H.
    - Cohn, Morris
    - Foster & Freeman
    - International Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Packard Motor Car Co.
    - Siloxicon; Egyptianized clay
  - 1906 (Box 24)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Bellefonte Academy, Bellefonte, Pa.
    - Day, David T.
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Foster & Freeman
    - International Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Packard Motor Car Co.
  - 1907
    - General
    - Acheson Co.
    - Brashear, John A.
    - Byrnes, & Townsend
    - Fitzgerald, Francis A. J.
    - Foster & Freeman
    - International Acheson Graphite Co.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Packard Motor Car Co.
    - Perkin, William H.
    - Williamson, Arthur M.
  - 1908 (Box 25)
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Mabery, Charles F.
  - 1909
    - General
    - Banbury, Fernley H.
    - Mabery, Charles F.
  - 1910
    - General, (2 folders)
    - Autobiography
    - Banbury, Fernley H.
    - Mabery, Charles F.
  - 1910 (Box 26)
    - Perkin Medal
  - 1911
    - General
    - Banbury, Fernley H.
    - Crookes, William
    - Farnsworth, Alfred W.
    - Mabery, Charles F.
    - Maury, Paul
    - Robinson, William V.
    - Ubbelohde, Leo
    - Wolcott, Clifton E.
  - 1912
    - General
    - Banbury, Fernley H.
    - Crookes, William
    - Farnsworth, Alfred W.
    - Kovalevsky, W. I.
    - Mabery, Charles F.
    - McAllister, David C.
    - Pfohl, Peter P.
    - Robinson, William V.
    - Russia, visit to
    - Russian Importing Co.
    - Schumacher, Willy
    - Takamine, Jokichi
    - Ubbelohde, Leo (Box 27)
    - Williamson, Arthur J.
  - 1913
    - General
    - Arrhenius, Svante
    - Banbury, Fernley H.
    - Bertolini, Mario
    - Bills
    - Crookes, William
    - Etzel, E.
    - Kovalevsky, W. I.
    - Laurento, Bruto
    - Mabery, Charles F.
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Ostwald, Wolfgang
    - Pfohl, Peter P.
    - Robinson, William V.
    - Russia, visit to, (3 folders)
      - General
      - Correspondence with Mrs. Edward Goodrich Acheson
      - Speeches
    - Russian Importing Co.
    - Schumacher, Willy
    - Sweden, visit to
    - Ubbelohde, Leo
    - Vickery, James Harris
  - 1914 (Box 28)
    - General
    - Armstrong, Henry E.
    - Crookes, William
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Farnsworth, Alfred W.
    - Hadfield, Robert A.
    - Kovalevsky, W. I.
    - Mabery, Charles F.
    - Maury, Paul
    - Pfohl, Peter P.
    - Rose, Frederick C.
    - Russian Importing Co.
    - Schumacher, Willy
    - Sweden, visit to
  - 1915
    - General
    - Acheson, Edward Goodrich, passport renewal
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Freeland, A. A.
    - Hadfield, Robert A.
    - Maury, Paul
    - McAllister, David C.
    - Rose, Frederick C.
    - Seaton, William Murray
    - Sweden, visit to
    - Water power legislation
  - 1916 (Box 29)
    - General
    - Baekeland, Leo Hendrik
    - British Ministry of Munitions of War
    - Day, David T.
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Heralds' College, London, England
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Maury, Paul
    - Seaton, William Murray
    - Vibe, J. C.
    - Water power legislation
    - Wayte (W. J.) Inc.
  - 1917
    - General
    - British Ministry of Munitions of War
    - Day, David T.
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Hadfield, Robert A.
    - Heralds' College, London, England
    - Liberty motor tests of "Oildag"
    - Marsh, Joseph W.
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Maury, Paul
    - Takamine, Jokichi
  - 1918 (Box 30)
    - General
    - Chandler, C. F.
    - Day, David T.
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Hadfield, Robert A.
    - Liberty motor tests of "Oildag"
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Maury, Paul
    - Takamine, Jokichi
    - Tryon, C. A.
  - 1919
    - General
    - Carson, E. F.
    - Day, David T.
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Hadfield, Robert A.
    - Harrell, C. E.
    - Herschel, Clemens
    - Kelly, James F.
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Maury, Paul
    - Texas Co.
  - 1920
    - General
    - Conservation
    - Day, David T.
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Edwards, Elisha Jay
    - Electrochemical Society
    - Harrell, C. E.
    - Holloway, James
    - Kelly, James F. (Box 31)
    - Mabery, Charles F.
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Mott, Samuel D.
    - Texas Co.
    - Tryon, C. A.
  - 1921
    - General
    - Archbutt, Leonard
    - Dunlap, Orrin E.
    - Kunz, George F.
    - Mabery, Charles F.
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Maury, Paul
    - Takamine, Jokichi
    - Tryon, C. A.
  - 1922
    - General
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Maury, Paul
    - Mellon, Andrew W.
    - Miner-Edgar Co.
  - 1923
    - General
    - Fitzgerald, Francis A. J.
    - Martin, T. Commerford
    - Mott, Samuel D.
  - 1924 (Box 32)
    - General
    - Maury, Paul
    - Mott, Samuel D.
  - 1925
    - General
    - Kuhn, Kuno
    - McDonald, John F.
    - Miner-Edgar Co.
    - Mott, Samuel D.
  - 1926
    - General
    - Arison, William H.
    - Federal Oil Conservation Board
    - McDonald, John F.
    - Mott, Samuel D.
  - 1927
    - General
    - Arison, William H.
    - McDonald, John F.
    - Mott, Samuel D.
  - 1928
    - General
    - Acheson Graphite Co., sale of
    - Electrochemical Society, Edward G. Acheson Fund
    - Jehl, Francis
    - Mott, Samuel D.
  - 1929 (Box 33)
    - Electrochemical Society, Edward G. Acheson Fund
    - Fitzgerald, Francis A. J.
    - Smithsonian exhibit
  - 1930
    - General
    - Mott, Samuel D.
    - Niagara Falls, N.Y., exhibit
    - Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., exhibit
    - Sweden, visit to
  - 1931
    - General
    - American Philosophical Society
    - Socony-Vacuum Oil Co.
  - 1933
    - General
    - Fink, Colin G.
  - 1936
  - 1939
    - Jehl, Francis
  - Biographer's papers (Raymond Szymanowitz) (Box 34)
    - 1953, Russia, visit to
    - 1954, Carborundum Co.
    - 1955
    - 1956
    - 1957-1960, Banbury, Fernley H.
    - 1962
    - 1963, Banbury, Fernley H.
    - 1964, Carborundum Co.
    - 1965-1966, Cowles Electric Smelting and Aluminum Co.
  - 1966
    - Carborundum Co.
    - Lürmann, F.
  - 1967
  - 1968
  - Undated, Bowman, Francis, "History of the Carborundum Co."
- Miscellany, 1872-1956 (Box 35-48)
  Financial notebooks, newspaper clippings, biographical material, printed matter, calling cards, commissions, memorabilia, scrapbooks, scientific notebooks, and court proceedings.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Acheson family history (Box 35)
  - Biographical sketch of Acheson
  - "Birth certificate" of the Carborundum Co.
  - Calling cards, visits to Russia and Sweden, 1913
  - Commissions See Oversize
  - Court proceedings, Electric Smelting & Aluminum Co. v. the Carborundum Co., 1894, (2 vols.)
  - Data regarding Acheson companies (Box 36)
  - Financial books, 1876-90, (5 vols.)
  - "Index to Acheson files" (partial card file) (Box 37)
  - Invitation to life membership in the Congressional Country Club, Bethesda, Md.
  - Newspaper clippings, (3 folders); (4 folders) (Box 38)
  - Newspaper clippings, including visits to Russia and Sweden in 1913>, (2 folders) (Box 39)
  - Printed matter, 1910-1956, undated (Box 40-43)
  - Printed matter (Box 44)
    - Edison Pioneers
    - Articles and speeches by Acheson
    - Articles and speeches by Acheson (Box 45)
  - Publicity
  - Scientific notebooks (Box 46)
    - 1872-1881, (5 vols.)
    - 1882-1889, (6 vols.)
    - 1890-1895, (9 vols.) (Box 47)
    - 1897-1910, undated, (7 vols.)
  - Scrapbook See Oversize (Box 48)
  - Scrapbook of clippings, 1899
  - Typescript of A Pathfinder, 1910
- Oversize (Box OV 1-OV 2)
  Commissions and scrapbook.
  Arranged and describing according to the series and container from which the items were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Commissions (Container 35)
    - Scrapbook (Container 48) (Box OV 2)
  - Notes and sketches
  - Printed matter